## Irina Lapteva

**&** 646-812-0164

irinahop@gmail.com

<u>irinalapteva.github.io</u>

in <u>irinalapteva</u>

#### Mission

I strongly believe in power of the arts to bring people together. In particular, the performing arts have always been at the core of my life and a key part of my identity. As an indigenous former ballerina with 2 Master Degrees and more than 15 years of work experience in nonprofit performing arts organizations, I am uniquely suited to innovate and enhance the arts and education landscape. Driven by a deep passion and a strong entrepreneurial spirit, I aim to create transformative experiences that resonate with diverse communities and contribute to the enduring success of organizations and artistic excellence.

### **Experience**

#### Managing Director, CityDance Conservatory

2018-2024

- Led and managed logistical, administrative work, and day-to-day operations.
- Collaborated and worked closely with the Artistic Director to design and improve programs, schedule and monitor class and rehearsal schedules, and cast and support repertory.
- Efficiently and effectively planned and organized year-round education programs and managed communications with the students and parents.
- Managed and supported hiring a team of around 30 faculty teaching artists, 5 full-time staff members, several contractor workers, guest artists, partners, parent volunteers, interns, workstudy teachers, and rehearsal assistants.
- Oversaw contract negotiations, created agreements, and managed payroll and other payments for all classes, rehearsals, workshops, events, intensives, and performances.
- Managed the annual budget of \$2M for year-round programs in coordination with the goals set by CEO and Artistic Director with the Board, created the budget for summer intensives, developed and managed the production budget to ensure efficient use of resources, as well as the budget for all other artistic projects and events.
- Planned and managed summer intensives in multiple locations around 9 different programs each summer with guest artists and partnering dance companies for different levels of dancers, ages 6 to 20.
- Successfully launched a few new summer programs with the Artistic Director and professional national and international dance companies as well as optimized summer intensive auditions and streamlined the enrollment process.
- Oversaw all production aspects from pre-production planning to the final performances.
- Served as Production Head and Stage Manager for all CityDance performances and Galas at Strathmore, Kennedy Center, Atlas Performing Arts Center, and other venues for up to 2K people in the audience for each performance.
- Supported fundraising initiatives and coordinated related events, including the planning and execution of the annual Gala performance and fundraising efforts in collaboration with the Artistic Director, Executive Director, and board members.
- Worked directly with marketing team to review marketing materials and photos, organize photo shoots and video recordings, support implementation of key marketing campaigns, and facilitate cross-functional communication among project stakeholders.
- Successfully launched students support services, such us support for juniors and seniors to get into colleges and dance companies, supported auditions, dance competitions, and student choreography projects.
- Led the organization into a swift transition to online classes via MS Teams during the COVID-19 pandemic with livestreamed performances, that not only kept all the Conservatory students and teachers, but also increased enrollment and after the pandemic brought the Conservatory to top 5% of prestigious Ballet Academies in the US.

#### **Director of Education Programs**, Brighton Ballet Theater (BBT)

2010-2018

- Designed, developed, and managed outreach and education programs at public schools, senior centers, and community centers, engaging annualy up to 500 participants directly.
- Coordinated a team of teaching artists, engaged volunteers and parents on the daily basis, while collaborating closely with classroom teachers, school officials, principals, and directors.
- Wrote grant proposals and reports for >\$200K and raised funds for education programs.
- Taught dance classes, staged and choreographed up to one-hour dance shows, and acted as a host and stage manager during the performances.
- Organized performances, lecture demonstrations, and other events, such as the Nutcracker ballet and the Annual Children's Festival "The World of Dance", at public schools and colleges for thousands of students.
- Facilitated the opening of two new branches at the Staten Island Jewish Cultural Center and Snug Harbor, and developed dance programs and managed registration and marketing.
- Created an initiative that promoted dancing for social causes in collaboration with the dance magnet of Intermediate School 228 public school while performing in theaters, schools, and hospitals to raise awareness about cancer among children. Produced and edited a short documentary movie about this initiative, which received the Silver Level Honorable Mention in the 2014 Speak Truth to Power National Film Competition in partnership with the American Federation of Teachers and the Tribeca Festival.
- Organized and taught dance and music education programs for children with Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD) in partnership with <u>American Autism Association</u>.

#### Board Member, Sakha American Diaspora

2022-present

- Advance the mission by establishing a network of indigenous peoples from the Sakha Republic, offering support for the preservation of languages, traditions, and spirituality, and promoting these unique cultures through educational and cultural programs in the US.
- Contribute as a team member in organizing the annual Sakha Summer Festival in a New York City park and attracting approximately 250 attendees with music and dance performances, exhibitions, and sports competitions.

#### Consultant, Academy of Dance and Creative Arts

2017

- Designed a new development strategy.
- Created new outreach and education programs that resulted in new grants.
- Assisted with the expansion of local community connections that brought new sponsors.
- Organized the marketing campaign for the premiere of the ballet *Cinderella*.

#### Studio Manager, Co-Owner, Flash Dancing and Ballet School

2007-2010

- Supported the opening of a new dance studio while designing and teaching dance programs.
- Administrated and coordinated dance classes, created budgets, and collected admission fees.

#### Ballet Dancer, Yakut State Theatre of Opera and Ballet

2005-2006

• Performed in ballets and operas, including leading roles as Mercedes in *Don Quixote* and Raymonda in *Raymonda*, as well as soloist roles in *Sleeping Beauty* and *Swan Lake*.

#### Education

• MA, Arts and Entertainment Industries Leadership, New York Institute of Technology	2017
• MA, Project Management, Synergy University	2011
• BA, Operational Management, Synergy University	2011
• BA, Ballet and Performing Arts, Poselskaya Yakut Choreographic College	2006

# Training

• International Programs Internship, <u>Joffrey Ballet School</u>	2016
aduate Assistantship, New York Institute of Technology	2016
• Development Internship, American Ballet Theater	2016